<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A philosophicall essay for the reunion of the langvages, or, The art of knowing all by the mastery of one</title>
            <author>Rose, Henry, fl. 1656-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11823009</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11823009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49612</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49612)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 547:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A philosophicall essay for the reunion of the langvages, or, The art of knowing all by the mastery of one</title>
                  <author>Rose, Henry, fl. 1656-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hen. Hall for James Good,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Rose. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Language and languages.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49612:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49612:1"/>
            <p>A Philoſophicall ESSAY for the REUNION OF THE LANGVAGES, OR, the Art of Knowing all by the Maſtery of one.</p>
            <p>OXFORD Printed by HEN: HALL for JAMES GOOD. 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49612:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49612:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the READER.</head>
            <p>MEeting by chance with this ingenuous offer, I thought it might not be improper ſince I found it in another dreſse, to make it ſpeak another Language too, which among the moſt creditable of Europe, hath not deſiſted from its claim to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: There are very few Nations but have, at ſometime or other, laid in their pretences to a ſupremacy for their Language, and have boaſted an aſſiſtance from unſuſpected reaſon and Authority: But however vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the controverſie hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd, the modesty, and ingenuity of this Author hath rendred, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne more plauſible, for having without any private regard (in ſuch caſes moſt uſuall to the ſpruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:49612:3"/>and flouriſhing Air of his owne Native tongue) made that noble Language of the Romans the Baſis of his project; And finding him throughout altogether free from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and partiality, I thought an anteview of ſo excellent and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a deſigne would not be unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the more ingenious part of the world, and that I ought not to neglect ſo faire an opportunity of recommending to their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that illuſtrious dialect, which as it is certainly of all others the most valuable, ſo to the ſhame of theſe modern ages, is either exceedingly impair'd or loſt in its familiar uſes among thoſe who challenge the title of the <hi>Beaux Eſprits</hi> of the times. The aime therefore of this Projector being to facilitate and expedite the Mastery of this as well as others, its ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb facs="tcp:49612:3"/>may poſſibly appear not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ungratefull if it be but in hopes to find this incouragement that we ſhall be able to reſerve ſome number of years from our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually tadious application to its ſtudy for other eminent uſes, and commence men &amp; Schollers at a much eaſier rate and in an earlier age then now commonly practic'd; I ſhould prevent the Author If I ſhould entertaine you with any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commendation of it them that he hath taken for his model the moſt creditable and plauſible Language of the world. If at any time you divert your ſelfe with reading No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels; you will here meet with notions that are both Philoſophicall and Airy, and in order to the maine deſigne for the moſt part purely ſcientifick and demonſtrative; and
<pb facs="tcp:49612:4"/>after If all you ſhall think that you have not miſpent your time by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomething that is either uſefull or pleaſurable I ſhall have my deſigne and the Author the credit.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49612:4"/>
            <p>AS the Knowledge of forreign Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages ought not to be reputed one of thoſe vain and uſeleſs curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that ſerve only to amuſe the mind, but is certainly conducive to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand different ends; ſo we ought not to think it ſtrange if our age, which gives ſuch aequall and ſecure judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the value of things ſhew more of paſſion then ever for it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the difficulties that are pretended. I am of an opinion, that one cannot do the world a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable piece of ſervice, then to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a certain and eaſie way to become univerſally acquainted with the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and to quit a ſubject from thoſe intrigues, in which the more knowing have at preſent involv'd it, either from a pure impotence to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingage it, or poſſibly from a fond
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49612:5"/>deſire of a freer breath of popular Air from thoſe who are ordinarily moſt taken with what they leaſt underſtand.</p>
            <p>This deſigne being only a proper entertainment for the moſt criticall of the Virtuoſes, I am the more incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to expoſe to the public, the project and plain I have form'd, before I intirely abandon the whole to their cenſure; that I may at firſt anticipate all manner of reply, and take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from the lights of the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht and intelligent perſons, if their zeale hath courage enough to make them willing to ſerve the world in their love and communication.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Authors deſigne.</head>
               <p>Moſt men being prepoſſeſt with two unjuſt prejudices againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Languages, th'one, that they have not all either reſemblance or accord among them, the other, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49612:5"/>they only depend upon the inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of chance, and the whifling toyiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of cuſtome, it might be thought no matter of extraordinary concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if one pretended to ſucceed in a ſtudy of this nature by the ſingle efforts of the memory, without either the vivacitie of imagination, or the force of reaſon being interreſſ'd.</p>
               <p>But being not very well perſwaded of the agreeableneſs of this method, in direct oppoſition to it, I have faſtn'd the whole deſigne in hand upon theſe two propoſitions:</p>
               <p>Firſt, that <hi>there is a certain accord between the ſeverall Languages:</hi> and that therefore they are attainable by compariſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>they are unquestionably founded upon reaſon,</hi> and therefore that muſt be made uſe of in their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall reference. It is upon theſe two foundations that I pretend to eſtabliſh the true method of gaining a maſtery
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49612:6"/>of the Languages, making it appear to the world by a ſenſible experience. that the mind can as eaſily make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon words, as upon the things they repreſent: <hi>Imagination</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> being the two faculties, that can reflect upon their objects, they both will appear in the preſent deſigne in their uſes ſuitable to their nature, the effects of <hi>Imagination</hi> ſhall be viſible in the ſeverall reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, and the inferences that are thence made; and it will be the worke of <hi>Reaſon</hi> to reduce all to certain prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, upon which the argumentative part muſt relye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49612:6"/>
               <head>The firſt part of the Deſigne.</head>
               <p>For the eaſier exerciſe of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, I ſhall acquaint you with a method that will appeare very naturall, by which inſteed of conſidering the Languages pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely in themſelves (as hitherto hath been uſuall) they may be compar'd one with the other without much difficultie, and at the ſame time their accord, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, and mutuall relation, diſcover'd either from the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of words, the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſcope or compaſſe, and the conformity of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. Tis true that this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and relation is not a little obſcur'd by the ſeverall od conſtitutions of mens minds, that checque at, and ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49612:7"/>with the firſt, and naked appearance without any farther inquirie; but withall its preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and eaſily perceiv'd by thoſe who are happy enough in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius for ſuch kind of Learning. Its ſomething like the paradoxes Geometry propoſeth upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and proportion of figures, where we are muſ'd at the firſt draught, and there appeares ſo little likelihood in them that the unexperienc't would take them only for the tricks and whims of a melancholique brain; whereas an ingenuous Artiſt, from the moſt naturall, and ſimple noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gradually conducts the mind to a kind of inſenſible diſcovery of truth, and makes it ſee on a ſuddain what it could not expect, and that with ſuch open aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as quit that from all ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49612:7"/>which but now had ſcarce any face of truth.</p>
               <p>Knowing no other method then this, that may be proper to make new diſcoveries in the ſciences I endeavour'd to make what uſe I could of it, ſo farr as my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject permitted; And ſince amidſt the ſeverall reſemblances of the Languages, there are ſome ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as neceſſarily grance upon the moſt unobſerving eye, I have ſo order'd my reflections, that by a reference to theſe, as models, I might by degrees ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at the knowledge of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which although reſerv'd, and ſometimes more diſtanc't, yet are neither leſs certain, nor reall: not unlike the ſubalternate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions in ſpeculation, which are not a jot the leſſe true for being farther remov'd from their firſt principle.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49612:8"/>
               <p>Thus tis that a Language with which we are already acquainted, either by the aſſiſtance of Art, or Converſation, leads us to anin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy with thoſe that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unknown to us before, and that their relation redreſſeth the treachery of the memory in the cloſe and juncture of one with the other.</p>
               <p>But that I may compaſſe this my deſigne with leſſe trouble, my greateſt care is to make choiſe of one Language as a rule to meaſure by, and a principle to reduce all the reſt too: for to pretend to compare them imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately one with another, as ſome would have it, is to cheriſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion among thoſe things that demand the moſt of order.</p>
               <p>The veneration that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had for antiquity, made me
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49612:8"/>think at firſt of ingaging for the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as being (for ought we know) the earlieſt, the moſt noble, and moſt naturall Language of the world and that from which all others, in a manner, derive themſelves. But it was not long before I began to conſider, that this would directly croſſe the firſt principles of my intended method, and appear a kind of indeavour to teach an unknown Language, by another, of which we have the moſt imperfect, and ſlender information of all. The kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and inclination I ought to have for my own Country, had almoſt perſwaded me to reſt my ſelf there, and to make my native tongue the baſis of this univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall reduction but then the reſt of the Europaean world (which I have no reaſon to ſlur or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49612:9"/>would have as ill reſented the project, as we did it in the Germans, who would long agoe have challenged this honour to themſelves. I had in the end no other courſe to take, but to throw my ſelfe upon the <hi>Latine,</hi> in which I luckily met with all the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conditions that did eaſily, and plauſibly conduce to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd attempt.</p>
               <p>To ſay the truth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a man of a judgement in ſuch things the moſt exact that ever was to take a <hi>meaſure</hi> from, demanded but three qualifications, <hi>viz. Univerſality, Certainty,</hi> and <hi>Proportion;</hi> that it ſhould be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally known to all thoſe that are to make uſe of it in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a meaſure, that it ſhould be ſixt, and determin'd in its ſelfe, and then that it ſhould be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49612:9"/>proportion'd to all thoſe things, to which it preſcribes their bounds, all which characters do with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage combine in the Latine, and that vvith ſuch propriety that they cannot be attributed to any other vvithout ſome ſort of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice; for the greateſt part of the other Languages they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termind to the extent of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Kingdom or Country, the Latine hath no ſuch diſadvantage upon it; It is to ſpeak proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Language of Europe: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Sciences have more enlarg'd its dominions, then all the conqueſts of the Romans, tis almoſt the common Idiom of the North, and univerſally knovvne to perſons of birth and educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vvho alone are preſum'd to ſtand in need of the aſſiſtance of forraigne Languages.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49612:10"/>
               <p>It diſownes the common im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of others, which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being ſubject to change, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by conſequence, ſerve for a certain determinate rule in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; and if it now ſurvive through the large extent of its entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it hath much the advantage of others, that are in a manner deceaſ'd to this that is fixt, and retaind by a well aſſur'd cuſtome and if its being univerſally known allows all perſons to ſhare its uſes, ſo its being ſteddy, and unalterable, ſecures it from all the uneven changes of time.</p>
               <p>As to its proportion, it in a manner keeps a mean between the Ancient and Modern Languages, it is neither altogether ſo pure as the one, nor ſo corrupt as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo with the ſame eaſe is applicable to both; and in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49612:10"/>is infinitely the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious, it being farre leſs trouble to paſſe from the mean to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, or from the extream to the mean, then to trace it from one extream to another. However this would ſeem incommodious beyond all redreſſe, to attempt to reduce all the Languages, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the moſt ancient, or elſe to any one of the moſt modern, becauſe in reality, the former have no more relation to the later, then theſe have with others of the ſame age, which have been as ſo many channels to derive Antiquity to us.</p>
               <p>Beſides the Latin makes a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meeting between the Eaſtern, and Weſtern Languages; as to the firſt alone it owes its birth and riſe, ſo the others do to it.</p>
               <p>It ſeems then no more difficult
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49612:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to attain the one, by ſtreaming it up to the fountain, then to gain all the reſt by making a like deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, by way of reſemblance to what we obſerve in nature when we diſcern, as well the effect by the cauſe, as the cauſe by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. In one word, to make up all the differences that may ariſe about the ſupremacie of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, I conſider the Latin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three different regards, as the <hi>daughter</hi> of the Languages of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> as the <hi>Mother</hi> of thoſe in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and as the <hi>Siſter</hi> of the more <hi>Northerne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it is abundantly copious, and rich, having been refind, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd for more then 3000. years by an infinite variety of nations, with whoſe ſpoyls it is now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted, ſo it may have a very great number of reſemblances, under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49612:11"/>which with little difficultie it will admit of a reference to all the reſt. For in concluſion, to reduce all to the moſt refin'd, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite Language, is not what I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to; the Barbarous ſtile of the ancient Romans will do me as much ſervice, as the quaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and elegance of Cicero; the Latin of the declining Empire, ſince the irruptions of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Nations, may be admitted into this deſigne to as good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as the language of Auguſtus his time; any ſenſe is the ſame of that of the <hi>Sciences,</hi> which makes one almoſt altogether di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from what is common and vulgar; the proper names of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, naturall Hiſtory, and Divinity, thoſe of Phyſick, and the Mathematicks, of Arts, Law, and Commerce; the names of il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49612:12"/>perſons, people and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of which Hiſtory furniſheth us with a plauſible account, will afford me no leſſe aſſiſtance on this occaſion, then the names of things that are moſt common.</p>
               <p>After having made choice of a Language in order to the deſign, I am in the next place to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my ſelf to a <hi>certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them,</hi> the reunion of which may be juſtly thought a modeſt and reaſonable attempt; for as there are ſome, the knowledge of which will be of very little uſe; ſo I am obliged to preſcribe ſome bounds to a deſigne that would lead me to ſomething indetermin'd, and infinite, and withall I ſuſpect the inlargement both of mind, and memory to compaſſe all; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering the conſequence of ſome to be indifferent, neither
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49612:12"/>that of Biſcany, nor the lower Brettaigne ſhould in my opinion much afflict any mans braine, nor do I believe that there are many more in the world intereſ't for them, then there are for the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Finland or Frizland, or the Barbarous jangling of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes and Savages. In the choiſe that I was to make I could not but give the preference to thoſe of the greateſt credit and repute, <hi>took ſome Prince</hi> (excuſe the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion) <hi>who having laid his deſign to reunite all the Kingdomes of the world, began his conqueſt upon thoſe Nations that were moſt formidable and renown'd, from an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that the reſt in a little time would be leſs able to make any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I am not of an humour to attempt any thing without an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49612:13"/>incouragement from reaſon, or to give my ſelfe any trouble through a kind of caprice, purely to gratifie my curioſitie; <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, State,</hi> and the <hi>Sciences</hi> are the <hi>three grand rules</hi> from which I make a judgement what Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are really the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant and noble; I have only therefore ſelected ſuch as <hi>Europe</hi> may uſe to the beſt advantage, either for the defence of the Church, the good of the State, the advancement of the Sciences, or the perfection of the moſt lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Arts. It is for this end that I have entertained in my deſigne all the Languages that concerne Religion, and make a particular mention of ſuch as furniſh us with originall texts, and the moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick tranſlations of the Bible, being of no means conſequence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49612:13"/>towards the faithfull interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſacred Records, and the confirmation of the Articles of our Creed.</p>
               <p>I am in the next place obliged to find a place for ſuch as concern and relate to State affaires, the moſt renowned E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pires, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and warlike Nations, which may afford a ſuitable entertainment for all ſorts of people, and withall very much conduce to the ſuccesful management of forraigne buſineſſe, the moſt important negotiations, Embaſſies, the tranſactions of war or peace, as well as the moſt hopefull deſignes of travellers. But above all I find my ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for thoſe that give us the moſt refin'd and polite diſcoveries of wit and Science, and have been cheriſht and nurſt up to our hands by the moſt knowing and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49612:14"/>of all Nations.</p>
               <p>I can hardly believe I ſhall meet with any inclinable to quarrell me for the number of 24. that I have thought on for my deſigne, ſince I preſume it no eaſie matter for the moſt nicely curious to find a juſt occaſion; and although there are none of them that are not unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably deriv'd from the ſame originall, it being no great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to convince any well ſettled head, that in the propriety of ſpeech there is but one mother Language: Yet to avoid confuſion I diſtribute them all into 7. different orders, as they ſeem to carry an immediate reference to the Languages, which are the commonly ſuppoſ'd origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals: ſuch are in the opinion of the Learned the <hi>Roman,</hi> and the <hi>Greec,</hi> the <hi>Teutonic</hi> and <hi>Sclavonic,</hi> the <hi>Hebrew, Scythian,</hi> and the <hi>Perſian.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49612:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The Roman Idioms are the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Spaniſh</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> which cannot now be unknowne to any but ſuch as are ſhamefully igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; <hi>I</hi> may adde likewiſe the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> which although not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry different from the <hi>Castilian,</hi> yet is not wanting in its owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar beauties, and hath receiv'd no mean acceſſion of uſe and honour from the conqueſts of its Kings in the moſt remote parts of the world.</p>
               <p>To the Greec <hi>I</hi> ſhall reduce its 3. principall relations, <hi>viz</hi> the Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Greec, ſuch as we meet with in our old Claſſic Authors, the vulgar, as it is commonly uſed ſince the declining age of the Empire at Conſtantinople, and the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique or Aegyptian, which is but a remainder of the famous govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Ptolomies in Aegypt:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49612:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>for although in its idiome there be ſomething yet remaining of an originall ſtamp, either in that its words ſeem to touch upon the auntient Language of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raous, or that its inflection no way reſembles the Greec, yet the Empire of Alexander and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors induc'd ſuch a confuſion, that the Greec hath almoſt got the better, and involv'd all the leſſer remains of Antiquity.</p>
               <p>Under the Teutonic <hi>I</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Almain or high German, the Flemmiſh or low Dutch, the Engliſh and the Daniſh, which is to this day entertain'd in the moſt Northerne regions, and may give us ſome intimations of a clearer light then any beſides, as having yet carefully ſecured ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the ancient Language.</p>
               <p>The Sclavonic is accompani'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49612:15"/>with 3. more conſiderable dialects the true Sclavonic, the Poliſh, and Muſcovitiſh, to which the valour of the Nations that ſpeak them have brought more repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation then any other ingenious performances.</p>
               <p>The Hebrew hath no leſs then ſeven in its retinue, the pure He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, ſuch as we meet with in our Bible, the Language of the Rabbins and Talmudiſts, the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee, the Syriaque, the Aethiopick or Abyſſin, the Samaritan, and the Arabique, which in our age hath ſo inlarg'd its dominion, that its either ſpoke or underſtood in the three parts of the Old World Aſia, Africa and Europe; and hath alone produc't ſuch a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious number of books, that one would ſcarce believe how a Nation ſo famous for its exploits in warr
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49612:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould have ſo much leaſure to attend to the improvement of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>The Scythian hath two very illuſtrious dialects in its traine, the Turkiſh and leſſer Tartarian, both which may ſerve in ſome meaſure to acquaint us what Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are uſed in the North of Aſia.</p>
               <p>The laſt is the Perſian, whch is not only univerſally priz'd in the Empire of the Sophy, but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon entertainment in the Court of the grand Seigneur, as well as in that of the Mogull, where it is hugely valued and eſteem'd.</p>
               <p>As this reference of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages to one another would be to litle purpoſe, if the leſs qualifi'd and accompliſht were not capable of judging of it, ſince tis for them principally I am moſt concern'd,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49612:16"/>I believ'd therefore it would be neceſſary intirely to retrench all that ſtrange variety of characters, whoſe od and fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſticall figures do ſtrangely divert the imaginations of thoſe, who are not well qualifi'd to conceive them. Neither do I intend to humour my ſelfe in that vaine kind of oſtentation that ſome affect, to make this kind of writing one of that moſt myſterious parts of their learning, but have found out a method of expreſſing the ſounds of all the diſtinguiſhing characters of each Language onely by the Roman, and that in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as eaſie and diſingag'd as it is accurate and new; inſomuch that the reſemblances of words, which altogether diſappear'd under thoſe uncouth figures (which like a veile intercepted them from the leſs cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify'd eye) preſently face the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49612:17"/>light, there being nothing left to interpoſe between them, and a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer conſideration, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhall not acquit me from my deſigne of diſcovering an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to decypher with eaſe all thoſe ſeverall kinds of writing, and of fixing them upon the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination in ſuch a manner as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty can admit of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
               <p>After having remov'd this firſt obſtruction, which hath ſo long imbroild and retarded the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Languages, that I may with leſs trouble reduce them to their firſt principle, I ſhall run near the ſame courſe, that hath been ſucceſſively taken in their removall, ſo farr as any hiſtory can informe us, upon which I prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally lay the ſtreſſe and baſis of my deſigne by producing ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49612:17"/>from it, the force of which cannot plauſibly be eluded. For I do not believe that any of the more curious will find fault with me for faſtning the origine, and alliance of the Language upon the ſame bottome with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and firſt ſociety of mankind, who are obſerved never to ſhift their Country, without having their Language to bear their Arms and Cuſtomes company. As I never thought fit to diſpute it with the Learned, why they did not make uſe of the affinity of the Languages, which ſometimes are of clearer notice to them to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the the firſt riſe of a people more remote, and with which they are leſſe acquainted; So I hope I may be permitted to make what advantage I can of the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations and colonies to give a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49612:18"/>clearer light to the beginnings and connexion of the ſeverall Tongues, there being ſomething near the ſame, or a like proportion between both: as for inſtance, To make good the opinion of Dionyſius Halicarnaſſeus, and Quintilian, who both pretend that the Latin tongue is no more then a Dialect of the Antient Greek, is but in plain and eaſie words to give an account of all the little ſettlements, and Plantations in Italy, which for ſome continuance of time was only inhabited by colonies from Greece.</p>
               <p>Upon what other terms I hardly underſtand this new project ſhould be ſurprizing to any, it being not the meer effect of imagination, or an humorous Idea, neither will it much ingage any ſort of people, but only ſuch as can eaſily diſlodge their prejudices when their owne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49612:18"/>lights ſhall aſſiſt in their convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that from ſuch aſſurances as ſhall be moſt free from ſuſpicion, being faithfull deductions from the hiſtories of the Colonies. But as it is impoſſible that the Languages ſhould not be liable to ſeverall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations and mixtures from the different aſſociations of people in ſeverall removes, ſo neither is it to be believ'd that this was done all on a ſudden; there ſeems to be a recemblance between the words that make up the Language and Traveſilers, who do not put off their accuſtom'd uſages and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſo ſoon as they arrive at a new Country, neither are they naturaliz'd, but with time and by degrees become maſters of the Air, humors, and qualities of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with whom they converſe.</p>
               <p>Since then this corruption is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49612:19"/>but of a graduall and intenſible growth, there is a neceſſitie, for its more certain diſcovery, of an orderly reflection upon the very firſt beginnings of the differences, being in the interim very ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to prevent a falſe retreat that might either ingage me too farr, or elſe in ſome unluckie cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, from which it would be no little difficulty to retire. And this ſeems to be the only way that I could find out to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certain Air and appearance of truth upon all that regard the preſent ſubject, which hath no farther a probability then what is given it from ſuch a carefull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, that ſhall ſuffer no paſs from one extreame to the other without touching upon that mean which is as it were the time of communication between both, for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49612:19"/>it is from this chain of words and ſequel of alterations that all the ſuitableneſſe, and likelyhood of this preſent method principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends.</p>
               <p>Although in reality there is no reaſon to doubt but that the French is a corruption of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, I could not however very eaſily perſwade my ſelfe that the word <hi>dechoir</hi> ſhould derive its ſelfe from <hi>cadere</hi> of the Latines, if I did not perceive all its ſeverall and diſtinct conveiances through the Alembic. They that firſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Language of the <hi>Romans</hi> inſtead of <hi>cadere</hi> made uſe of <hi>cader,</hi> as the Italians do to this day, who commonly cut off the final vowels where they obſeve them to follow Liquids. They that came after proceeded yet farther in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment, and from <hi>cader</hi> form'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49612:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>caer,</hi> as the Spaniards now uſe it, by taking away the letter <hi>d</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ordinary cuſtome, when it is ſeated in the middle of words. There are another ſort of people yet more ſturdy and blunt in their formes of ſpeech, who would ſay <hi>Car</hi> or <hi>Ker</hi> by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the two Vowels into one, as is obſervable among the Peaſants of France, and thoſe of Picardy, who retain very much of Antiquity, which ſeems to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with the manner of ſpeech among the Ancient French, who delighted to ſhorten and contract their words as much as poſſible, that they might make up a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage altogether as free as their humour; ſome of the moſt remote of theſe would inſtead of <hi>Ker</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Cher</hi> by a change of that firm and ſurly letter into one more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49612:20"/>eaſy and ſoft as we yet find it Cuſtomary in the remains of ſome of the Ancient Romans, and then after all by the turn of a Vowel into a Dipthong, from <hi>Cher</hi> is form'd <hi>Choir,</hi> which now begins to be out of date altho its Compoſit <hi>dechoir</hi> be ſtill of plauſible and commendable uſe. Thus 'tis that <hi>Cadere, Cader, Care, Car, Ker, Cher, Choir,</hi> and <hi>Dechoir</hi> make up but one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire chain and connexion, yet all to very little purpoſe if any one of the degrees by chance ſhould have been wanting.</p>
               <p>For this reaſon altho I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every Language in its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perfection, yet for clearing its originall in rendring this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of words more open and palpable I have been oblidg'd to make numerous reflections upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49612:21"/>the older forms of ſpeech as well as Orthographie, by which a better diſcovery may be made of all the varieties that occure in pronunciation, as alſo of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall medlies and Gibriſh of the Provinces of Each Empire that ſpeak the ſame Language, but moſt of them in a ſingular faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>So that it is moſt certain that that Language which is moſt quaint and polite is very often the leſſe, pure and moſt debaucht, if we make an acquall judgment from its originall which is the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable rule: Upon which account the dialects of Province, Gaſcogne, Languedoc, and that which is known by the name of the Antient Gauls is infinitely leſſe alter'd and diſtanc't from its original, then the Languages of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49612:21"/>the Court and Nobility, who take a pleaſure in receding from the Latin: Thoſe of Lombardy and Naples are for the moſt part leſſe corrupt than theſe of Siena and Florence; Altho the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards have a ſaying among them, that the Catalonian and that of Arragon is commonly more pure then the Caſtilian that is more Pompous. And not to ſpare the French more then the Spaniard, if they have reaſon to boaſt their Language to be the moſt refin'd and Polite of the world, yet their Neighbours might juſtly returne upon them, that of all the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects of the Latin, there is none more degenerate than theirs, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as its quaintneſs ariſeth from its ſweetneſſe, ſo that it is not attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable without a ſtrange deſcent from its principle. Thus <hi>le Capo</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49612:22"/>of the Italians, <hi>le Cabo,</hi> of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, <hi>le Cap,</hi> of the old French and <hi>le Kef</hi> of Picardy are all vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly alterd from <hi>Caput</hi> of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, but none ſo much as <hi>le Chef</hi> of the French, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing claims the ſame Originall.</p>
               <p>But this is not all; as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance and connexion of the Languages is not alwaies the ſame but depends more or leſſe upon the communication of the Nations that ſpeak them, So it's not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that this method ſhould be invariable, it muſt admitt of alteration with its ſubjects, and accomodate it ſelfe to the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Tongues.</p>
               <p>There is much more of Art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to reduce thoſe which only carry a reſemblance in their words, and abundantly leſſe for thoſe which withall admitt of an ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49612:22"/>in inflexion, And Since the ſame words which allow of this accord may have it in ſeverall diſtinct manners they are not all (if I may be permitted to ſay ſo) neither of Kin, nor alliance in the ſame degree; their relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſometimes nearer, Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at a greater diſtance, for we may by way of analogie diſcours at the ſame rate of the genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of words as we do of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of conſanguinity; for if the one fort be rang'd under the ſame Line either direct or Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall, the others admitt of a little deflection and do not exactly core<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond; ſome are allied in the firſt, ſome in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> degree, ſome in advancing from the branches to the ſtock, others in a deſcent from that to the branches, in a word this accord is neither always im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49612:23"/>nor at all directly oppoſite.</p>
               <p>I add beſides that as there are, ſome allied two or three ways and that ſince the firſt diviſion have contracted new and cloſer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſo I confeſſe there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that content themſelves with their Originall reference, and that have ſcarce any other agreement among them than what depends upon the common tie and union that they have with their firſt principle, which in reallity is no more then this famous Mother Tongue of which ſome make a myſtery without well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what they ſay: For altho it hath ſubſiſted in its ſelfe before the firſt confuſion, yet we muſt not think of diſcourſing of it at the ſame rate, nor put our minds upon the haraſſe of receiving it.</p>
               <p>'Tis no more now as ſome fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49612:23"/>imagaine a particular and diſtinct Language from others, ſo that there is but one way to regain it and reeſtabliſh it at leaſt ſo far as is neceſſary for a compleat execution of my deſigne, and that is to make a judicious choice of all that is primitive and moſt ſimple a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Remains of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Language either by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the firſt combinations of ſounds or by a regard to the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ideas of the mind, that were apply'd to theſe ſounds; to the end that we may referr thither by a ſequel, all the eſſentiall and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall words of each Language as to their fountaine; which admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of diviſions, runnes now in leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſtreams which aſſume the names of Originalls; becauſe they have their riſe from that grand Source where the firſt inhabitants of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49612:24"/>world ingroſt all. So that it may be truly ſaid of this Mother Tougue that it is in no ſenſe a part as being really every where either in ſums of its diviſions, or in its effects and dependances ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like your vertues of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements and the originall ſeeds of things, that Subſiſt not of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but in the mixtures that compoſe them.</p>
               <p>I ſhall poſſibly be wonderd at, that being able to accompliſh all by this ſingle method, I have not in the interim recours to it, when all other ways prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable; But after all, tho this method be perhaps more ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and of a more profound ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, it is not however the moſt naturall and compendious, be it never ſo refind'd or acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate to my deſigne, and I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49612:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>hardly underſtand the reaſon why any man ſhould affect a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and uncouth road to active at his purpoſe when the ſtreight lyes before him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of the deſine.</head>
               <p>Compariſon alone is not (in the opinion of ſome) ſufficient to accompliſh the preſent intention, however accurate it be; if it want the ſupports of <hi>reaſon,</hi> it may rationally be ſuſpected for being more airy then ſolid, and without injuſtice the ſame character may be given to ſome of thoſe unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall Chances that ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the moſt ſurprizing effects. Beſides altho the vivacity and force of imagination be eaſily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the relations of the Languages, and leaves there forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impreſſions, yet it neither war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants certitude, nor diſlodgeth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49612:25"/>confuſion; 'tis reaſon alone that eſtabliſheth the mind in its cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizances, and credits all its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions with order, tis that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone which perfects the combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all their relations and agreements according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall connexion which they have with the ſame principles on which they depend in Common.</p>
               <p>That which ſeems to be of greateſt moment is that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples be plauſible and rationall and ſuch as man may lay a ſtreſs on without ſuſpicion or fear, and this is that which in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular manner the principles of this Art challenge to themſelves, being in my opinion infinitely more ſenſible then thoſe which Philoſophy propoſeth under the characters of uncontroleable truths; I have therefore taken them all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49612:25"/>from the very natures of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of which I am treating <hi>viz:</hi> from the deflections and different regards under which the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of words may be manag'd; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may laſt of all ſerve for an aſſurance, that chance hath not all that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and authority, that is given it over the Languages; and that it would be no great difficulty to make it appear, that in the Languages themſelves there are well fram'd and ſolid reaſons, for every thing that appears o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and hath been hitherto ſuppos'd to be the bare effect of Caprice.</p>
               <p>It may be perceiv'd by the very effects themſelves that it will make up a ſcience fully demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative, and back't with ſuch conſequences, as may very well paſſe for compleat models in this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49612:26"/>kind: And above all the ſcope of its principles infinitely ſhortens the way without being at all oblig'd to make a deſcent to a thouſand taedious and weariſome differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which appear much better, and in a more elegant manner in their principles then in themſelves, which is an incouragement for me to hope that a Language for the acqueſt of which we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by a cloſe application num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſeverall years, will by this means be made the divertiſement of ſome hours, or at moſt but ſome few days.</p>
               <p>Words being in the opinion of all men but ſignificant ſounds, they may be taken either as they are <hi>Natural ſounds,</hi> or <hi>arbitrary ſigns,</hi> I would ſay, either as they are the proper effect of the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our organs, or as the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49612:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>repreſentation of the thoughts of our minds. And ſince they make their paſſes from one Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to another they cannot well admit of any alteration in this their tranſit but in three reſpects; for whatſoever change be ſuppos'd it will neceſſarily fall out, either in the <hi>ſounds themſelves</hi> that compoſe the words, or in <hi>their ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> or in their <hi>different modifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and its from theſe three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct regards that the generall principles have their riſe, upon which I have faſtn'd this new Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime of the Philoſophie of the Languages.</p>
               <p>That I may make my proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure more juſtificable and artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, I examine with all exactneſſe the different organs of the voice, the various motions of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcles belonging to theſe organs,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49612:27"/>and the admirable concent and accord of thoſe motions; and theſe I make uſe of to demonſtratively explaine the preciſe number of all the ſimple ſounds, that enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the compoſition of the Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to diſcover the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per pronunciation of theſe ſounds, and by conſequence to diſcloſe their nearneſſe and affinity, the reſemblances of ſome, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion of others, their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and oppoſition, their Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and Antipathy, in a word, all their combinations and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, their diviſions and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, their orders and ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. From whence I conclude that all the aſtoniſhing and ſurprizing depravations and Corruptions that are met withall in the words that one Language borrows from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, in changing or in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49612:27"/>in adding or retrenching, have their baſis in nature; which never attempts any thing but to the purpoſe, and with a ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous care, when to us it appears to have acted with an open and obſervable neglect.</p>
               <p>We may Study Nature upon the Latine it ſelfe which may ſerve as well for a model as it doth for a principle; It will in the firſt place acquaint us that the Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are almoſt accounted for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for altho there are ſome of them that admitt of eaſie chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges among themſelves according as they are more open or reſerv'd, we know nevertheleſſe that there are none of them but what may be abſolutely ſhifted into the place of another of what kind ſoever, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately, or by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and degrees. For a finall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49612:28"/>of this we have no more to doe but to make an eaſie compariſon of the different deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative of the ſame word, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of theſe three <hi>Cepa; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio</hi> and <hi>occupo,</hi> to the Verb <hi>Capio</hi> may ſerve for an inſtance, if we ſhall but grant the truth of this principle which the orienta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts have always ſuppos'd, who form the greateſt part of their words from the ſole change of their Vowels.</p>
               <p>The ſame is not altogether al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable in relation to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, where we muſt not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt indifferently all ſorts of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; the ſole affinity of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans is that which muſt regulate almoſt all their varieties: the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biall letters eaſily ſupplant one another but the Dentall or Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guall with more difficulty ſucceed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49612:28"/>them as being not of the ſame order; For as theſe conſonants, M. B. P. V. F. make neer the ſame ſound, which is modified by the divers force of the Air, opening the lips after ſeverall forms. So the Letters D. T. Z. S. ought to make an order by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, having a particular rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the point of the tongue, which only by touching upon the teeth in various manners frame their pronunciation.</p>
               <p>But it is not a ſingle and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie reflexion, that can abſolutely determine whether two letters have reſemblance and proportion, becauſe there are ſome of them that being made up of the move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſeverall organs, may be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently alter'd according to their various reſemblances, ſo the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>H.</hi> carrys not only the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49612:29"/>of a gutturall as it is pronounc'd by the aſſiſtance of the muſcles of the throat, but alſo as an Aſpiration beſides the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it hath to the whiſpers of the tongue, and the 6. Aſpirates of the Lips, Teeth, and Palate. However if the precipitance or forwardneſſe of any, hath by chance brought into uſe, other methods of altering ſounds, as they have not ſo certain a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in reaſon, ſo neither can they be receiv'd within the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas of this Art, at leaſt being not eſtabliſht by a regular and conſtant analogie.</p>
               <p>From the ſound of words, I paſſe to their <hi>ſignification,</hi> which in the ſame dialect may be call'd the ſoul of a word, as the ſound is its body; to expreſſe it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther terms, then what ſeem to rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49612:29"/>the dry and unpleaſant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Pedant or Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian; I ſuppoſe that words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the expreſſions of our thoughts, and our thoughts the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of objects, the different ſignifications that are given to words, principally depend upon the various conceptions, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Nation frames of the ſame objects, agreeable to what ſeems moſt neerly to concern it.</p>
               <p>This ingageth me to explaine the intire ſequel, and naturall dependances of our Ideas, and the manner of their forming, of which the world hath yet receiv'd a very imperfect account. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this, you may underſtand what thoſe objects are, of which we have proper Ideas, and what thoſe are which we conceive by forreigne images, and that we
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49612:30"/>do not name but in figurative terms; whence ariſeth that alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and reſemblance of our Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, and why the greateſt ſhare of our words if refer'd to their firſt originall, are but metaphors which repreſent objects to us in ſuch terms as are proper to another, with which it hathſome agreement, or neere relation, and withall what are the grand principles of meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors; either of Attribution or Proportion, that do not only make up the beauty, but almoſt the intire body of the Language.</p>
               <p>Our Anceſtors that gave no names to things, but by a directing prudence, purpoſing to diſtinguiſh the works of Nature and Art, had an eſpeciall regard to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reſemblance they had with any thing that was moſt known to them, and that was already di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſht
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49612:30"/>by its character, or to any one of their moſt prevailing properties, or to the principall action that diſtinguiſht them from other beings. They made uſe of almoſt the ſame arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to impoſe names upon things more expreſſive of their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by conſidering them only with reference to their operations, of which they were the immediate principles. As for the operations, themſelves being not aequally knowne, nor aequally obvious to ſenſe they plac't the ſame ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in the terms they made uſe of to repreſent them, that Nature hath eſtabliſht in our apprehenſions and cogniſances.</p>
               <p>There being therefore nothing in the world of which they could have fram'd a more diſtinct Idea, then of the <hi>motion</hi> of bodies; which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49612:31"/>is obvious to all the ſenſes, we muſt nor wonder if conſidering Locall motion as the firſt and principall object of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they afterwards gave no names to the Operations of each being, but ſuch as ſeem'd to expreſs ſome relation either to motion in generall, or to its different ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or to ſome one of its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances, ſuch as are place, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, ſituation, extention, Union and ſeperation, in a word to all the reſemblances and agreements that in any way or kind relye upon motion. For if Modern Philoſophy that Studies Nature by a cloſer application then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, pretend to a clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent explication of Naturall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the referring them all to the <hi>Sole movement of matter</hi> as their true cauſe; there is much
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49612:31"/>more reaſon that in order to the giveing an account of all that is to this day paſt among the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, we ſhould have recours to ſuch terms as are expreſſive of motion, ſince it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but that all others that are reducible, may be referr'd hither as to the firſt principle of their ſignification.</p>
               <p>Beſides motion is allow'd a far greater Scope and extent among the Languages then in Nature for 'tis to that we referr our moſt refin'd and ſpirituall conceptions I mean ſuch as we frame of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations of our ſouls and the propenſions of our wills, So when we ſay that the mind or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding applyes it ſelf to think to conceive, to diſcours, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to diſimbroile to diſingage a buſineſſe, to diſcover a truth; when
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49612:32"/>we talke of troubles, averſions, of hurries and conſternations of the ſoul, to expreſſe ſuch actions as are moſt remote from ſenſe, we make uſe of ſuch Images as are corporeall in their firſt originall, although for the moſt part they have loſt their proper ſignificance to aſſume ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is purely figurative.</p>
               <p>'Tis by theſe Principles Ireduce to naturall reaſon all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ways by which words alter their primitive ſignification to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace another, either more inlarg'd or reſerv'd, or never ſo little diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifi'd either in Proportion or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance; for tis no eaſie matter for words to travell from one Country to another without meeting with the ſame caſualties, that uſe to befall forreign Plants which are ſeldome remov'd into a new ſoile, but dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and either loſe ſome of their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49612:32"/>Native virtue, or acquire ſome new. But moſt people having met with this generall propoſall, to expreſſe at firſt appearance, what they think with as little trouble as is poſſible, it thence falls out that to ingroſſe a great deal of ſenſe in few words, they ſcarce allow enough preciſely to marke out the ſimple ideas of their minds, fitted out to all their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall reſemblances, they that are moſt ſimple in themſelves, are commonly compounds in their ſignifications, neither is there any one of the leaſt conſiderable, but what is diverſify'd in each Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage by a thouſand different mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difications.</p>
               <p>From thence proceed all the methods of inflexion, derivation, and compoſition that give being to the moſt ſubtle kind of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49612:33"/>all the ſpecies and forms of Nouns, Verbs, and particles that make up the aeconomy of a Language, together withall diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Numbers, Genders Caſes tenſes Modes, and Perſons which have more of Art than at firſt ſight is imagin'd, for the Cuſtome of Nations hath not only autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd theſe inventions to vary the Cadence of words, but with an admirable facility to expreſſe all the deflexions, by which an Idea of the ſame object may be repreſented to our conceptions according as it admitts of a mixture of reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, which it may have either to its effects or Cauſes, or as it is related to the ſeverall eſtates, wherein it ſubſiſts, to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of time or place, and to all the circumſtances that may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it, either within or without
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49612:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>us. As the more ſenſible differences of the Languages principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in all theſe modifications; ſo one of the greateſt, ſecrets of this Art is to know how choiſly to ſelect and diſtinguiſh, both in our ideas and in the words that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, that which is principall and eſſentiall from what is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceſſory, ſubtly to difference the firſt ideas from the ſecond, the ſecond from the third, the ſimple from the Compound, the primitive and Originall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from its dependances and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, its modifications and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reſtrictions, in one word (if I may ſo expreſſe it) not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the habit with the perſon. For in a manner theſe modifications are the ſame words, that the habit is to the body; this new dreſſe that is given to forreign words
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49612:34"/>to fitt them up alamode to the Country, for the moſt part time ſo diſfigures them and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them ſo obſcure, that they impoſe as well upon our eyes as ears, and paſſe for originalls and Natives of the Country, although in reality they are borrow'd from our Neighbourhood, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time from beyond the ſeas.</p>
               <p>To make a ſecure judgement therefore of the originall, there remains nothing but to conſider them all, naked and intirely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoil'd of all that trompery that diſguiſ'd them; and that this may be done with more ſafety we muſt follow them ſtep by ſtep in their travels, and eſpie out the different ranges they have taken and the habits they have ſhifted, to come thus vizarded and maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued to us.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49612:34"/>
               <p>Theſe are the moſt inlarg'd principles and infallible ways by which I diſcover this ſecret and miſterious accord of the Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which without doubt will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo much the more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as haveing been never to this hour been believ'd that they had any ſuch cloſe tie or relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But theſe principles may be apply'd ſeverall ways, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaſt they ſhould continue undermin'd, I make it appear by the ſequel, what in particular muſt be done in each Language in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to its genius and proper Character, This is that which obligeth me to make an exact inquirie into the nature of thoſe Languages I pretend to reduce, I do not content my ſelfe infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly to take my draught either
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49612:35"/>in the generall conſent of nations, which are as often cheated in their Ideas they have of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of each Nation as they are commonly in its manners, or from the particular ſentiments of the more knowing or Learned, who without any preoccupation of mind have ſtudied their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Language with more then ordinary care. But to make all yet more certain, I principally form my examinations from the very hiſtory of the Languages, which is the moſt aequall rule we can take our meaſures from, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the preſent deſigne.</p>
               <p>In order to this, tis neceſſary that we make reflexions upon the firſt beginnings of each Nation, and that from other memoires then ſuch with which we are for the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49612:35"/>moſt part furniſh't by the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and ſeriouſly to examine the continuall comerce it hath had with the moſt conſiderable of its neighbours, the wars, feuds and Leagues of its Governours with other Princes, the irruptions and invaſions of Conquering Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that have corrupted its Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as they ingroſt its ſpoils, the frequent Colonies that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors have ſent thither beſides its voyages at Sea, and its traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, with the moſt remote plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Theſe are the more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate cauſes of this confuſion and mixture.</p>
               <p>It may perhaps withall be no mean pleaſure to ſee the baſis of each Language diſtinguiſht from the changes and acceſſions of time or revolutions of State, what eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49612:36"/>Nation hath contributed of its owne to inrich it, what Religion, the Government and what Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have communicated to it, what it retains of Antiquity and what new acqueſts it hath made to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve its loſſes with advantage.</p>
               <p>Afterall, this is yet but the ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, or at moſt but the body of a Language, Its neceſſary that this rude and indigeſted maſſe made up of ſo many different dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects ſhould be animated by ſome ſecret ſpirit that ſhould expand it ſelfe through all its parts and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall members, and reduce them to unity by communicating the ſame air to them, and that this Spirit or Soul ſhould be the individuall principle of all the effects, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible changes, which make us ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſtinguiſh one Language from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49612:36"/>another: The Temper, Humour, and Nature of a people, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of their minds, their genius and particular guſts, their more generall and forcible incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, their ordinary paſſions, and ſuch ſingular qualities, by which one Nation is remarq'd and diſtinguiſht from another, are the moſt evident ſigns to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the true genius of a Language, becauſe they are in reality the immediate cauſes, and the very o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginalls after which I have copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all my draughts to compleat the preſent piece, which in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is not wanting in ſomething that is very Naturall, Beſides this, the very manners and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of Nations, their Laws and policy, and their publick tranſactions, both of peace and war, are things ſo univerſally
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49612:37"/>known, that there is no need of any farther ſearch, how to be bale to judge by proportion of the genius, and characters of the Languages ſo ſecurely, as by that of the people that ſpeak them.</p>
               <p>But as the care of a Nation to improve and advance the Arts and ſciences and other kinds of good Learning, is that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes moſt to the perfection of its Language, So tis upon the manner in which its receiv'd, and the characters of its Authors, that I cheifly depend to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether it be modeſt or imperious, whether it relliſh more of a ſoftneſſe, ſweetneſſe, and delicacy, than of a certain Noble briſque and generous air, whether it incline more to the ſimplicity of Nature, or the ſubtile refine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Art, whether it be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49612:37"/>to affectation, or betray a certain negligence which hath its graces too, as well as its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Art, and laſt of all whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a little crampt in attempting to be too exact, or elſe better accomodate it ſelfe by its freedome from all reſtraint.</p>
               <p>Having diſcoverd the genius and proper character of each Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, I have fram'd the moſt perfect Idea that is poſſible, by way of analogie with the principles of the Platoniſts, with whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I was always as much taken as I am diſſatisfy'd with their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>This Idea being unmaſqued ſerves me in the ſequell for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule, to eſtabliſh the true and proper reaſons of all that paſſe for ſingular and remarqueable in each Language, either in relation
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49612:38"/>to the choice, the mixture, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſounds, the force and ſignifications of words, or the Air and manner of expreſſion; For tis moſt certain that all theſe things are alter'd according to the genius of a people: So the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards would diſtinguiſh themſelves from other Nations by their haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, and affected gravity, and their words are eaſily underſtood by a certain pompous Air, that ſeems to border upon grandeur and Majeſty: On the Contrary the Italians are the Nation of the world that ſeems to be moſt fond of its pleaſure, and its naturall, that this ſoftneſſe ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to their Language, and that all their words ſhould breath nothing, but what is ſweet, polite, and the moſt exact harmony; their compoſitions admitt of no
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49612:38"/>ſounds but ſuch, as can ſlatter the Ear, they ſuffer not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of conſonants, whoſe rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may never ſo little offend the Organ, but they are extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Love with Vowels, and often allow their ſequences to make their pronunciation more ſweet and delicate. For their ſignification, that they might mixe an accord with their energie, they have hardly any but what are more or leſſe figurative, from a perſuaſion, that a Metaphor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents objects to the mind in that moſt curious and diverting manner, and withall they are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to make choiſe of none, but ſuch as repreſent the faireſt images: They are no leſſe ſollicitous to diverſifie their words by agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble modifications, their inflexion hath very little uneaſie in it, it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49612:39"/>is all of it aequally facile and gay; their diminutives are exceedingly relliſhing, becauſe there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than ordinarily pretty in them, they are rich in deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and compounds, not only becauſe their pronunciation is more harmonious, but alſo becauſe they expreſſe themſelves in a more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall manner, In one word they baniſh every thing that may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ingratefull, and are paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in queſt of all that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the Sweetneſſe of their Language.</p>
               <p>My ſenſe is much the ſame of other Languages, but becauſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelfe may be ſuſpected by ſome, eſpecially if at any time it appear too juſt or plauſible, I was the rather concern'd ſo to order my inſtances, that beſides the induction, I intended cuſtome
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49612:39"/>and experience ſhould ſupport reaſon, and reaſon ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme experience, and withall the examples are ſo naturally chain'd with their principles, and all of them ſo diſtributed in their proper places, that without ſo much as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the leaſt reflexion, I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptibly comprize all the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall and eſſentiall words of each Lauguage, being willing my ſelfe to draw all my concluſions from the principles I have mention'd, and to make all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary inductions, without leaving any thing of trouble or diſeaſe to the reader, who in ſuch caſes is glad to be quitt from paines and inconvenience, I have ſome hopes, that a compoſition thus differently made up of Hiſtory, reflexions and Criticiſmes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by principles, deductions,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49612:40"/>and examples may contribute ſomething to the agreeableneſs of the deſigne, and lett off a ſubject that of it ſelfe is dry and knotty enough, without making it more unacceptable by that mean and diſreputed method, that hath ſo much decry'd the Critiques, and ordinarily hath given a diſguſt to a ſcience before it hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the leaſt conſideration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that didacticque way, is by no means proper in the preſent caſe, for as there is little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in being taken notice of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the character of a Scholler, ſo the only remedy is to contrive ſome way to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things without lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſuſpicion of having a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee in groſſe and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the whole deſigne expreſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49612:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>in as few words as the brevity of the ſubject would permitt me; And However rationall it may be in it ſelfe yet it wants not its adverſaryes; Some with a great deal of heat, plead that if this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod acquiring the Languages, hath any thing in it that is Curious by way of ſpeculation, it is how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever uſeleſſe enough in relation to its practice, ſince <hi>Cuſtome</hi> and <hi>Converſation</hi> only (ſay they) is the great Maſter of Language, and that we muſt intirely relye upon memory and the aſſiduity of conſtant and reſolv'd induſtry.</p>
               <p>Others confeſſe that it hath in earneſt its advantages, but doubt much of the poſſibility of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, hardly beleeving that the Languages have in good truth ſuch an accord and reſemblance as I ſuppoſe they have, or that there
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49612:41"/>is a poſſibility for the witt of man now to diſcover it.</p>
               <p>By way of reply to the firſt, I confeſſe that one thing I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at, is that perſons ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ingenuous ſhould ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare themſelves againſt the judgement in favour of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, I have a very great regard to their qualitie and worth, but cannot ſubmitt my ſelfe to their opinion, The only way (as I i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine) to Learn the Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and that in what number we pleaſe, to do it with eaſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taediouſneſſe, confuſion, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loſſe of time, and without the common hazard, of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with as much eaſe as we acquire them with difficulty, and to be maſter of them all in ſuch a manner, as ſhall relliſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is mean or not become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49612:41"/>a Rationall man, is in one word, to attribute more to the judging and reflecting faculty then to the memory; for if the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory depend and relye only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reflexions of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we have no reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect much from its ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, for however plauſible it may appear, it will always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow, limited, confus'd, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; its laction is not vigorous enough to take us off from thoſe fatigues that diſtaſt our moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enterprizes, and its efforts to weak and Languiſhing in a little time to execute a deſigne of ſo large a compaſſe as this; being ſo determin'd as it is, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ſhould reduce ſo great a number of Languages ſo diſtanc't in appearance one from another; If at any time it ſeem extraordinary
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49612:42"/>in an action, its Species are ſoon diſplac't by their multitude, and when they are rang'd in the beſt order imaginable, they continue not ſo long without being either effact by thoſe that ſupervene or diſappearing of themſelves, haveing nothing that can fixe and retaine them, So that the Languages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo vaſt an extent, there is no reaſon that the memory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhould be confided to for their acqueſt, unleſſe we could be content to ſacrifice an infinite ſpace of time to the Sole know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of words, which being ſo valuable as it ought to be to us, may be imployd with more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and ſucceſſe, either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the cognizance of things or the management of buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>To ſatisfie others, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more at preſent to ſay to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49612:42"/>them but that if the deſigne ſhall appear to them at firſt ſight ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fantaſticall or temerarious, the execution will ſoon juſtifie me, and perhaps convince them that it is not always rationall poſitively to paſſe a judgement upon any thing before a cloſe and a narrow ſearch, and that we ought not haſtily to deſpaire of any thing; the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which hath not been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted all imaginable wayes.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, as I do not beleeve my ſelfe to be deceiv'd in that which make up the groſſe and main of the deſigne, ſo I do not expect that all that I ſhall advance in the ſequel upon this connexion of the Languages, ſhould be receiv'd by all for uncontroule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able truths, of which I my ſelfe am ſufficiently perſwaded; I am too well acquainted with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49612:43"/>of truth to beleeve my ſelfe ſo ſuccesfull as to have alwayes diſcover'd that in the moſt imbroyld and the moſt doubtfull affaires of the world; yet I confeſſe that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that great reſpect that is due to it, I have in ſome caſes leſſe regarded it when it did not appear to comply with the capacityes of ordinary men, perſuading my ſelfe that conjecture well fram'd and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted by a plauſible Air is more relliſhing to ingenious perſons, then an obſcure and fainting truth, of which ſort there is a very great number in the preſent ſubject.</p>
               <p>I propoſe then to the Learned, this new ſyſteme of the Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, not as an inconteſtable Theſis in all its parts but only as an Hypotheſis, not altogether irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall and which beſides hath this particular advantage, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49612:43"/>it ſhould be the falſeſt thing in the world in ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it may at leaſt be allowable in the practice, And I hope to receive the ſame favour that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (that were moſt obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolv'd againſt his Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis) granted Copernicus by their confeſſion, that let it be never ſo falſe it is however the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to uſe and Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall ſupputations.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
